You may never have heard of Kenema, Sierra Leone
يمكن ألا تكونوا قد سمعتم قبل ذلك عن كينيما، سيراليون
or Arua, Nigeria.
أو أوروا، نيجيريا.
But I know them as two of the most extraordinary places on earth.
ولكني أعرف أنهم أكثرالأماكن غير العادية على الأرض .
In hospitals there, there's a community of nurses, physicians and scientists
في المستشفيات هناك ، يوجد مجتمع من الممرضين، الأطباء والعلماء
that have been quietly battling
يحاربون بهدوء
one of the deadliest threats to humanity for years:
واحدا من أكثر الأخطار المميتة للبشرية لسنوات :
Lassa virus.
فيروس لاسا .
Lassa virus is a lot like Ebola.
فيروس لاسا يشبه الإيبولا كثيراً .
It can cause a severe fever and can often be fatal.
يمكن أن يُحدث حُمي شديدة وفي كثير من الأحيان تكون قاتلة .
But these individuals, they risk their lives every day
لكن هؤلاء الأشخاص، يعرضون حياتهم للخطر كل يوم
to protect the individuals in their communities,
لحماية الأشخاص في مجتماعاتهم،
and by doing so, protect us all.
وبذلك، يحموننا جميعا .
But one of the most extraordinary things I learned about them
ولكن واحدة من أكثر الأشياء غير الاعتيادية التي تعلمتها عنهم
on one of my first visits out there many years ago
في واحدة من أولى زياراتي هناك منذ عدة سنوات
was that they start each morning --
كانت أنهم يبدأون كل صباح --
these challenging, extraordinary days on the front lines -- by singing.
هذة التحديات , أيام غيرعادية في الصفوف الأمامية -- بالغناء
They gather together, and they show their joy.
إنهم يجتمعون معاً، ويظهرون فرحتهم .
They show their spirit.
يظهرون أرواحهم.
And over the years,
وعبر السنيين،
from year after year as I've visited them and they've visited me,
عاما بعد عام عندما أزورهم ويزورونني،
I get to gather with them and I sing
أجتمع معهم وأغني
and we write and we love it,
ونكتب ونحب هذا،
because it reminds us that we're not just there to pursue science together;
لأن هذا يذكرنا أننا لسنا هنا لمتابعة العلم معاً فقط،
we're bonded through a shared humanity.
نحن مرتبطون معاً عن طريق إنسانيتنا المشتركة .
And that of course, as you can imagine, becomes extremely important,
وهذا بالتأكيد، كما يمكنكم أن تتخيلوا، أصبح مهماً جدا،
even essential, as things begin to change.
وحتي أساسيا، كشيء لبداية التغيير.
And that changed a great deal in March of 2014,
وهذا غير شيئا كبيرا في مارس 2014،
when the Ebola outbreak was declared in Guinea.
عندما تم إعلان وباء الإيبولا في غينيا .
This is the first outbreak in West Africa,
هذا أول وباء في غرب إفريقيا،
near the border of Sierra Leone and Liberia.
بجانب حدود سيراليون و ليبيريا .
And it was frightening, frightening for us all.
وكان هذا مخيف، مخيف لنا جميعا.
We had actually suspected for some time
كنا في الحقيقة مشتبها بهم لبعض الوقت
that Lassa and Ebola were more widespread than thought,
كان لاسا و إيبولا ينتشروا أكثر مما كان متوقع،
and we thought it could one day come to Kenema.
وقد قلنا أنه من الممكن أن يأتي يوما ما لكينيما.
And so members of my team immediately went out
وهكذا خرج بعض الأعضاء فوراً من فريقي
and joined Dr. Humarr Khan and his team there,
وانضموا ل د.هومار خان وفريقه هناك،
and we set up diagnostics to be able to have sensitive molecular tests
وأعددنا تشخيصا لنكون قادرين على الحصول على اختبارات حساسية جزئية
to pick up Ebola if it came across the border
لنمسك بالإيبولا إذا جاء عبر الحدود
and into Sierra Leone.
و داخل سيراليون .
We'd already set up this kind of capacity for Lassa virus,
كنا بالفعل أعددنا هذه الاختبارات لفيروس لاسا،
we knew how to do it,
لقد عرفنا كيف نقوم بهذا،
the team is outstanding.
كان الفريق رائعا .
We just had to give them the tools and place to survey for Ebola.
لقد كان علينا فقط أن نعطيهم الأدوات والمكان ليستطلعوا للإيبولا
And unfortunately, that day came.
وللأسف، أتى ذلك اليوم .
On May 23, 2014, a woman checked into the maternity ward at the hospital,
في 23 ماي 2014 دخلت امرأة قسم الولادة في المستشفى،
and the team ran those important molecular tests
وأجرى الفريق تلك الاختبارات الجزيئية المهمة
and they identified the first confirmed case of Ebola in Sierra Leone.
وحددوا أول حالة مؤكدة للإيبولا في سيراليون .
This was an exceptional work that was done.
كان هذا عملاً استثنائياً قد تم .
They were able to diagnose the case immediately,
كانوا قادرين علي تشخيص الحالة فوراً،
to safely treat the patient
ليعالجوا المريض بأمان
and to begin to do contact tracing to follow what was going on.
و يبدأوا اتصال تتبعي لمعرفة ماذا كان يحدث .
It could've stopped something.
لقد أوقفت شيئاً.
But by the time that day came,
ولكن مع حلول ذلك اليوم
the outbreak had already been breeding for months.
الوباء كان قد إندلع لشهور ؟
With hundreds of cases, it had already eclipsed all previous outbreaks.
بمئات من الحالات , إنه قد طغى بالفعل علي كل الأوبئة السابقة .
And it came into Sierra Leone not as that singular case,
وأتي إلى سيراليون ليس كحالة فردية ,
but as a tidal wave.
ولكن كموجة كبيرة .
We had to work with the international community,
كان يجب علينا أن نعمل مع المجتمع العالمي ,
with the Ministry of Health, with Kenema, to begin to deal with the cases,
مع وزارة الصحة , مع كينيما . لنبدء في مواجهة تلك الحالات ,
as the next week brought 31,
حيث جلب الأسبوع التالي 31 ,
then 92, then 147 cases -- all coming to Kenema,
ثم 92 , ثم 147 حالة -- كلها قادمة لكينيما ,
one of the only places in Sierra Leone that could deal with this.
واحدة من الأماكن الوحيدة في سيراليون القادرة علي مواجهة هذا .
And we worked around the clock trying to do everything we could,
ولقد عملنا علي مدار الساعة نحاول أن نفعل أقصي ما نستطيع ,
trying to help the individuals, trying to get attention,
في محاولة لمساعدة هؤلاء الأشخاص , في محاولة لجذب الانتباه ,
but we also did one other simple thing.
ولكننا أيضاً فعلنا شيء آخر بسيط .
From that specimen that we take from a patient's blood to detect Ebola,
من تلك العينة التي أخذناها من دماء المريض لنكتشف الإيبولا ,
we can discard it, obviously.
نستطيع أن نخرجه, بوضوح .
The other thing we can do is, actually, put in a chemical and deactivate it,
الشئ الأخر الذي يمكننا فعله, في الواقع , أننا نوقفه كميائياً ,
so just place it into a box and ship it across the ocean,
نضعه فى صندوق ثم نرسله عبر المحيط ,
and that's what we did.
وهذا هو ما فعلناه .
We sent it to Boston, where my team works.
أرسلناه لبوسطون , حيث يعمل فريقي
And we also worked around the clock doing shift work, day after day,
وعملنا علي مدار الساعة نقسم العمل علينا في مناوبات, يوما بعد يوم,
and we quickly generated 99 genomes of the Ebola virus.
و سريعاً أنتجنا 99 جينوم لفيروس الإيبولا .
This is the blueprint -- the genome of a virus is the blueprint.
هذا هو المخطط -- الجينوم الفيروسي هو المخطط .
We all have one.
كلنا لدينا واحد .
It says everything that makes up us,
إنه يقول كل شيء داخلنا ,
and it tells us so much information.
ويقول معلومات كثيرة جداً .
The results of this kind of work are simple and they're powerful.
النتيجة من مثل هذا العمل بسيطة وقوية .
We could actually take these 99 different viruses,
يمكننا بالفعل أخذ هؤلاء ال99 فيروس المختلفين ,
look at them and compare them,
مشاهدتهم ومقارنتهم ,
and we could see, actually, compared to three genomes
ويمكننا أن نري , فى الواقع مقارنة لثلاث جينات
that had been previously published from Guinea,
وقد حدث هذا سابقاً ونشر من غينيا,
we could show that the outbreak emerged in Guinea months before,
يمكننا أن نظهر بداية الإندلاع في غنيا منذ شهور مضت,
once into the human population,
مرة واحدة للبشر,
and from there had been transmitting from human to human.
ومن ثم أنتقل من إنسان لأخر .
Now, that's incredibly important
الأن , هذا مهم جداً
when you're trying to figure out how to intervene,
عنما تحاول أن تعرف كيف تتدخل ,
but the important thing is contact tracing.
ولكن الشيء المهم هو التتبع .
We also could see that as the virus was moving between humans,
يمكننا أيضا أن نري أن الفيروس خلال إنتقاله بين البشر,
it was mutating.
يتحور.
And each of those mutations are so important,
وكل تحول من هذا مهم جدا,
because the diagnostics, the vaccines,
بسبب التشخيص, والتطعيمات,
the therapies that we're using,
والعلاجات التي نستخدمها,
are all based on that genome sequence, fundamentally --
كلها مبينة على هذا التسلسل الجيني, في الأساس --
that's what drives it.
هذا ما يقوده.
And so global health experts would need to respond,
وهكذا خبراء الصحة العالميين عليهم الرد ,
would have to develop,
يجب أن يتطوروا ,
to recalibrate everything that they were doing.
ليفحصوا كل شيء كانو يفعلوه .
But the way that science works, the position I was in at that point
ولكن طريقة عمل العلوم, والمكان الذى كنت فيه في تلك اللحظة
is, I had the data,
كان, أن لدي المعلومات,
and I could have worked in a silo for many, many months,
كان بإمكاني العمل في صومعة للكثير, الكثير من الشهور,
analyzed the data carefully, slowly,
أحلل المعلومات بحذر, بتمهل
submitted the paper for publication, gone through a few back-and-forths,
أقدم الورقة للنشر , أمر خلال عدة محاولات ذهابا وأيابا ,
and then finally when the paper came out, might release that data.
وأخيراً عندما تنشر الورقة , يمكننا الإفصاح عن المعلومات .
That's the way the status quo works.
هذة هي الطريقة التي يعمل بها الوضع حالياً.
Well, that was not going to work at this point, right?
حسنا, هذا لم يكن ليفيد في هذه المرحلة, صحيح ؟
We had friends on the front lines
كان لدينا أصدقاء في الصفوف الأمامية
and to us it was just obvious that what we needed is help,
و بالنسبة لنا كان واضح أن ما نحتاجه هو المساعدة ,
lots of help.
الكثير من المساعدة .
So the first thing we did is,
وهكذا أول شيء فعلناه هو ,
as soon as the sequences came off the machines,
بمجرد أن التسلسل خرج من الماكينات ,
we published it to the web.
نشرناه على الإنترنت .
We just released it to the whole world and said, "Help us."
لقد نشرناه للعالم كله وقلنا, "ساعدونا."
And help came.
وأتت المساعدة .
Before we knew it,
قبل أن نعرفها,
we were being contacted from people all over,
كان يتم الاتصال بنا من جميع أنحاء العالم,
surprised to see the data out there and released.
أنبهروا برؤية المعلومات في الخارج هناك ومنشوره .
Some of the greatest viral trackers in the world
البعض من أعظم متابعي الفيروسات في العالم
were suddenly part of our community.
أصبحو فجأة جزئاً من مجتمعنا .
We were working together in this virtual way,
كنا نعمل معاً في هذا الطريق الافتراضي ,
sharing, regular calls, communications,
مشاركة, مكالمات منتظمة, تواصل
trying to follow the virus minute by minute,
نحاول أن نتتبع الفيروس دقيقة بدقيقة ,
to see ways that we could stop it.
لنجد طرق لإيقافه .
And there are so many ways that we can form communities like that.
وهناك الكثير من الطرق التي يمكن أن نكون بها مجتمعات مثل هذه.
Everybody, particularly when the outbreak started to expand globally,
الجميع , خصوصاً عندما بدأ الوباء في الانتشار عالميا,
was reaching out to learn, to participate, to engage.
كان يصل للخارج ليتعلم , ليشارك , ليلتحم .
Everybody wants to play a part.
الجميع يريد أن يلعب دوراً .
The amount of human capacity out there is just amazing,
كمية القدرات البشرية في الخارج هناك كانت رائعة ,
and the Internet connects us all.
والإنترنت جمعنا كلنا .
And could you imagine that instead of being frightened of each other,
ويمكنكم أن تتخيلوا هذا بدلا من أن نكون خائفين من بعضنا البعض ,
that we all just said, "Let's do this.
هذا كل ما قلناه , "لنفعل هذا .
Let's work together, and let's make this happen."
لنعمل معاً , ولنجعل هذا يحدث ."
But the problem is that the data that all of us are using,
ولكن المشكلة كانت أن المعلومات التي نستخدمها جميعاً ,
Googling on the web, is just too limited to do what we need to do.
البحث على الإنترنت , محدود للغاية لنفعل ما نحتاج أن نفعل .
And so many opportunities get missed when that happens.
وبهذا فرص كثيرة ضاعت عندما حدث هذا .
So in the early part of the epidemic from Kenema,
ولذلك في الجزء المبكر من الوباء في كينيما ,
we'd had 106 clinical records from patients,
كنا قد سجلنا 106 حالة من المرضى ,
and we once again made that publicly available to the world.
و مرة أخرى فعلنا هذا علانية متاحاً للعالم .
And in our own lab, we could show that you could take those 106 records,
وفي معاملنا , إستطعنا أن نظهر أنه يمكنكم أن تأخذوا ال 106 سجل،
we could train computers to predict the prognosis for Ebola patients
يمكن أن ندرب الكمبيوتر للتنبؤ والتكهن بمرضى الإيبولا
to near 100 percent accuracy.
بنسبة دقة 100% تقريباً .
And we made an app that could release that,
و صنعنا تطبيق يمكن أن ينشر هذا ,
to make that available to health-care workers in the field.
لجعل هذا متاح لعمال الرعاية الصحية في الميدان .
But 106 is just not enough to make it powerful,
ولكن 106 ليست كافية لجعل ذلك قوياً ,
to validate it.
لتكون مثبتة .
So we were waiting for more data to release that.
لذلك نحن منتظرين معلومات أكثر لإصداره .
and the data has still not come.
وتلك المعلومات لم تأتي بعد .
We are still waiting, tweaking away,
مازلنا منتظرين , نناور بعيدا ,
in silos rather than working together.
في الصوامع بدلاً من العمل معاً .
And this just -- we can't accept that.
وفقط -- لا يمكننا القبول بهذا .
Right? You, all of you, cannot accept that.
صحيح ؟ أنتم , جميعكم , لايمكنكم القبول بهذا .
It's our lives on the line.
إنها حياتنا على الخط .
And in fact, actually,
وفي الحقيقة , فعليا ,
many lives were lost, many health-care workers,
خسرنا الكثير من الأروح كثير من عمال الرعاية الصحية ,
including beloved colleagues of mine,
ضمنهم زملاء أعزاء لي ,
five colleagues: Mbalu Fonnie, Alex Moigboi,
خمس زملاء مبالو فوني , أليكس موج بوي ,
Dr. Humarr Khan, Alice Kovoma and Mohamed Fullah.
د. هومار خان , أليس كوفاما ومحمد فولا.
These are just five of many health-care workers
هؤلاء فقط خمسة من الكثير العاملين بالرعاية الصحية
at Kenema and beyond
في كينيما وما حولها
that died while the world waited and while we all worked,
ماتوا بينما ينتظر العالم وبينما عملنا جميعا ,
quietly and separately.
بهدوء وعلى إنفراد .
See, Ebola, like all threats to humanity,
إذن, إيبولا, مثل كل الأخطار على البشرية,
it's fueled by mistrust and distraction and division.
إنها موقدة بعدم الثقة والارتباك والانقسام .
When we build barriers amongst ourselves and we fight amongst ourselves,
عندما نبني حواجز بيننا ونتحارب بيننا ,
the virus thrives.
يزدهر الفيروس .
But unlike all threats to humanity,
ولكن ليس كباقي الأخطار على البشرية ,
Ebola is one where we're actually all the same.
الإيبولا هو الوحيد الذي نكون نحن جميعاً متشابهون فيه .
We're all in this fight together.
نحن جميعاً في تلك الحرب معاً
Ebola on one person's doorstep could soon be on ours.
إيبولا على عتبة شخص ما يمكن أن يصبح قريبا على عتباتنا .
And so in this place with the same vulnerabilities,
ولذلك في هذا المكان بنفس نقاط الضعف ,
the same strengths, the same fears, the same hopes,
ونفس نقاط القوة , نفس المخاوف , نفس الأمال ,
I hope that we work together with joy.
أتمني أن نعمل معاً بفرح .
A graduate student of mine was reading a book about Sierra Leone,
طالب تخرج لدي كان يقرأ كتاباً عن سيراليون ,
and she discovered that the word "Kenema,"
وإكتشفت كلمة "كينيما,"
the hospital that we work at and the city where we work in Sierra Leone,
المستشفى التي نعمل بها والمدينة التي نعمل بها في سيراليون ,
is named after the Mende word for "clear like a river, translucent
سميت من كلمت ميندي تعني " نقاء مثل النهر , شفافة
and open to the public gaze."
ومفتوحة لنظر العامة . "
That was really profound for us,
هذا كان عميق جداً بالنسبة لنا ,
because without knowing it, we'd always felt
لأنه بدون معرفة هذا , كنا نشعر دائما
that in order to honor the individuals in Kenema where we worked,
أنه تكريماً للأشخاص في كينيما حيث كنا نعمل ,
we had to work openly, we had to share and we had to work together.
علينا أن نعمل بانفتاح , كان علينا أن نشارك وأن نعمل معاً
And we have to do that.
وكان يجب أن نفعل هذا .
We all have to demand that of ourselves and others --
علينا جميعاً المطالبة بهذا لنا وللأخرين --
to be open to each other when an outbreak happens,
لنكون منفتحين لبعضنا عندما يحدث وباء آخر ,
to fight in this fight together.
للمحاربة في هذه الحرب معاً .
Because this is not the first outbreak of Ebola,
لأن هذا ليس أول وباء للإيبولا
it will not be the last,
ولن يكون الأخير ,
and there are many other microbes out there that are lying in wait,
ويوجد الكثير من الميكروبات الأخرى في الخارج منتظرين ,
like Lassa virus and others.
مثل فيروس لاسا وأخرين
And the next time this happens,
والمرة القادمة لحدوث هذا ,
it could happen in a city of millions, it could start there.
يمكن أن يحدث في مدينة مليونية , يمكن أن يبدأ هناك .
It could be something that's transmitted through the air.
يمكن أن يكون شيء ينتقل عبر الهواء .
It could even be disseminated intentionally.
يمكن حتى أن يكون نشر عمداً .
And I know that that is frightening, I understand that,
وأنا أعلم أن هذا مخيف أنا أفهم هذا ,
but I know also, and this experience shows us,
ولكني أيضاً أعلم , وهذه التجربة سترينا ,
that we have the technology and we have the capacity
أن لدينا التكنولوجيا ولدينا القدرة
to win this thing,
للنجاح على هذا الشيء ,
to win this and have the upper hand over viruses.
لننجح على هذا ونكون ذوي الكلمة العليا على الفيروسات .
But we can only do it if we do it together
ولكن يمكننا فقط إذا فعلناها معاً
and we do it with joy.
وإذا فعلناها بمرح .
So for Dr. Khan
وذلك ل د.خان
and for all of those who sacrificed their lives on the front lines
و لكل هؤلاء الذين ضحوا بحياتهم في الصفوف الأولي
in this fight with us always,
في هذه الحرب معنا دائماً ,
let us be in this fight with them always.
لنكون معهم في الحرب دائما ,
And let us not let the world be defined
ودعونا لا نجعل العالم معرف
by the destruction wrought by one virus,
بالدمارالذي أحدثه فيروس واحد ,
but illuminated by billions of hearts and minds
ولكن مضاء ب مليارات القلوب والعقول
working in unity.
يعملون في وحدة .
Thank you.
شكراً لكم .
(Applause)
(تصفيق)